How can I be polite in English?
That&#39;s what Marta wants to know.
How do I know that
I&#39;m being polite
or having good manners in England?
Obviously, you can say things
like &#39;please&#39; and &#39;thank you&#39;,
but let&#39;s look
at some more ways to be polite.
To be polite in English,
we generally use indirect language,
as direct language can sound
a bit rude.
What do you want?
Here are some ways you can be
less direct and more polite.
So, giving opinions.
It can sound a bit rude
to give your opinion in a direct way.
Your presentation was too long.
To be less direct,
use verbs like &#39;reckon&#39;, &#39;feel&#39;, &#39;guess&#39; and
vague language like &#39;a little&#39;, &#39;sort of&#39;,
&#39;kind of&#39;.
I reckon your
presentation was a little too long.
You can also turn it
into a question to be more polite.
Don&#39;t you think your presentation
could be a little shorter?
For requests,
if you ask them in a direct way,
they can sound a bit rude.
Oh, give me a lift, will you?
Instead, use modals.
Can you give me a lift, please?
Use past or continuous forms,
or even both.
I was wondering if you could possibly
give me a lift to Scotland this weekend?
You can use question tags.
You couldn&#39;t give me a lift,
could you?
You can also use
introductory phrases like:
&#39;Would you mind?&#39;
Would you mind giving me a lift,
please?
&#39;When you have time&#39;
If you have time,
could you read over this report?
Saying &#39;no&#39;.
We find it hard
in English to say &#39;no&#39; directly.
It can sound a bit abrupt.
Are you free Friday night?
I&#39;m having a party.
Nah.
Instead, we use unsure and tentative language.
Use expressions like &#39;I&#39;m not sure&#39;,
&#39;I doubt&#39;, &#39;probably&#39;.
I&#39;m not sure I&#39;ll be able to make it.
And remember,
giving a reason is much more polite.
I think I might be away then.
When talking about
problems and mistakes,
if you&#39;re direct, it can make the
other person feel very uncomfortable.
My pay is wrong this week.
To talk about problems
in a less direct way,
use verbs like &#39;seem&#39;, &#39;appear&#39;, or &#39;look&#39;.
Erm, there seems to be a problem
with my pay this week.
It looks like there&#39;s a
little mistake with my pay this week.
Or you can use the passive form.
I think a mistake has been made
with my pay.
Finally, learn some set phrases
for being polite.
What?
Instead of &#39;what?&#39;,
&#39;pardon?&#39;
Pardon?
Instead of
&#39;leave me alone&#39;,
try, &#39;Could I just have a moment, please?&#39;
Instead of &#39;move&#39;,
&#39;Excuse me. Please.&#39;
Instead of &#39;What do you want?&#39;,
&#39;Can I help you?&#39;.
Now, I&#39;d be very grateful if you could read the information below for more help.
And please, when you get a moment, would you mind sending us your own questions?
Here&#39;s our email address.