I would say yes. All women, including
me, know the feeling of being afraid in
public space.
&gt;&gt; As a woman, you just keep a much closer
eye on your surroundings.
&gt;&gt; This man was behind me filming me while
I was jogging.
&gt;&gt; I didn&#39;t. Cut it out.
&gt;&gt; We live in a society that shrugs its
shoulders at the fact that half the
population can&#39;t move freely in public
spaces.
The effect of city was tremendous.
Everybody was scared. Police have hunted
the hagaman since 1998.
&gt;&gt; People had a pair of scissors in their
jacket. one of the most feared serial
rapists in the country.
&gt;&gt; Women went to selfdefense classes.
&gt;&gt; Look at me. Hello. I&#39;m talking to you.
&gt;&gt; That&#39;s the classic. We&#39;d rather send
women to self-defense courses than talk
to men about violence.
&gt;&gt; It&#39;s very important that you listen.
Violence and sexist remarks are their
easy solution. The model we&#39;re aiming
for will hurt a bit more.
First question, who knows someone who&#39;s
experienced some form of sexualized
violence,
whether it&#39;s sexual harassment in public
spaces or anything else?
The second question, who knows a person
who has committed sexualized violence?
Feel free to look around.
[music]
And then a last question.
Who knows a person who has committed
sexualized violence and has been held
accountable for it? [music]
It&#39;s often said that the most dangerous
place for a woman is her own home. It&#39;s
true domestic violence is rampant and
many women experience violence in their
relationships. At the same time, we
mustn&#39;t forget that every woman
experiences violence in public spaces,
too.
&gt;&gt; This man was behind me filming me while
I was jogging.
&gt;&gt; I did not.
&gt;&gt; So, show me again in the deleted folder.
&gt;&gt; I was already heading back when it
happened. You can imagine a long main
road on my right. On the left, forest,
trees, greenery.
I just come from running around a pond.
Beautiful water. Just stunning.
[music]
Then I noticed there was a shadow, a
person on a bicycle about 1 and a half
meters behind me.
As a woman, you just keep a much closer
eye on your surroundings.
Then everything happened all at once.
Put that away.
&gt;&gt; I want to check the video is deleted.
&gt;&gt; Yes, it is.
&gt;&gt; Why is it still not deleted?
&gt;&gt; What?
&gt;&gt; It&#39;s still not deleted. Click on it.
&gt;&gt; Yes.
&gt;&gt; Why is it still there?
&gt;&gt; Oh man. Delete. Permanently delete this
video.
Yes.
And back again to the folder to the
overview.
&gt;&gt; Very good. Why do you do that? I don&#39;t
know either.
&gt;&gt; Yeah, I don&#39;t usually. Honest.
&gt;&gt; Well, you better never do it again.
It was pure luck that I had a phone with
me that still had enough battery and
that I even thought of filming it
because most of the time you don&#39;t even
notice something like that.
You are filming me while I&#39;m jogging.
Luckily, I noticed it cuz I was
wondering why there was a shadow behind
me.
It&#39;s bad enough as a woman in this world
and you&#39;re one of the men who makes it
that way.
When I saw that woman&#39;s video, I thought
very brave. The way she reacts to the
sexual harassment is incredibly
quick-witted.
Her reaction was by the numbers, if you
will. She confronted him, made him
delete the video.
In reality, it&#39;s hard to react that way.
A very important message to all those
affected by sexual harassment in public
spaces is to be aware that any reaction
you have is appropriate.
&gt;&gt; [music]
&gt;&gt; The only inappropriate thing in a
situation like that is the behavior of
the perpetrator.
My perception of public space is
different because of course every
negative experience heightens the
insecurity and skepticism.
One thing I think isn&#39;t talked about
enough is public space.
So much more could be done to increase
at least the sense of safety for women.
Um has worked with [music] gender
equality in urban planning since the
late 1970s and it&#39;s always been an
important focus for the municipality.
&gt;&gt; [music]
&gt;&gt; We have a lot of international attention
and also exchanges with other cities and
of course that&#39;s something that makes us
uh very proud because we think that we
have done a lot of good things.
[music]
So my name is Anika Dalan. I work as a
gender equality officer uh here in the
municipality of UMIO at the department
of strategic development. In general, we
know that women as a group feel less
safe in public space than men. So we&#39;re
going to do a little bit of walking in
the city center and then we&#39;re going to
take the bus up to the So if we
construct places in public space where
people feel unsafe have we know that
that will disproportionately restrict
women&#39;s movement in public space.
&gt;&gt; This tunnel it&#39;s a walking and bike
passage under the railway.
We know that people feel safer in public
space in the company of other people and
women feel especially safer in the
company of other women.
There&#39;s an artwork with quotations from
Sara Leadman, which is a local author.
And there&#39;s also recordings of her voice
that you can press and listen to when
you go through.
Even though it&#39;s not an actual physical
woman, but kind of the company of Saleim
Man&#39;s words gives a sense of comfort or
security.
You will also see that the corners in
the tunnel are rounded to kind of take
away the feeling that somebody could
hide behind the corner and and jump out.
There&#39;s an exit also in the middle. If
you you feel unsafe, you can also exit.
We sometimes get that question. So now
can you guarantee that nothing will
happen here? We didn&#39;t build a magical
place. It&#39;s still a place used by human
beings.
And we see that people use it a lot. And
that&#39;s the most important factor to
create safety in public space is to have
people.
But we need to remember that we also
simultaneously [music]
have to work with norms and attitudes in
uh society and how we treat [music] each
other.
[music]
We need to remember that women are not
afraid of places. Women are afraid of
men. [music]
[music]
Hman hogaman
&gt;&gt; hogan
&gt;&gt; hogaman
[music]
&gt;&gt; the case of hog manan really affected
how people in Umo felt about public
space
um was a quiet place in 1998
people locked their cars but on the
countryside everybody didn&#39;t lock their
house when they got to
Okay,
&gt;&gt; this is it.
I don&#39;t know.
&gt;&gt; I work with the Hogaman case in
different magazines, different TV shows.
I&#39;ve been in radio. I wrote a book about
the Hogaman.
&gt;&gt; [music]
&gt;&gt; And so it&#39;s sort of followed me over the
years.
[music]
So this is the one.
&gt;&gt; Yes.
The Hugman case is special in UMIO. He
was active as far as we know from 1998
to the end of 2005.
Here you can see the escape. He ran
under the bridge. He assaulted about 10
women. It&#39;s been seven years from first
to last.
&gt;&gt; It was attempted murder.
&gt;&gt; Going out in the evening really scared
me.
&gt;&gt; There&#39;s nothing you can do. As a young
woman, you feel so unsafe.
It
&gt;&gt; sort of forced a whole city to the knees
for so many years.
We&#39;re at the University of Im. This is
the location where the uh the attack and
the attempted murder uh in March of 2000
took place. A woman was walking home
from a student pub when she was attacked
by Hogaman. He left her to die
unconscious in snow without shoes.
So this is the map of Hoga and this is
the university. The security guard was
on his shift. It was 3:00 in the night.
He was checking doors at the university
and then he suddenly saw something
unusual on the ground.
And when he got closer, he realized
there was a unconscious human being.
She survived
thanks to a security guard.
Then it got quiet
for a number of years. It felt like Umo
got back to his normal. He was gone
until the end of 2005.
During that time there was a lot of
focus on safety in public space.
You know on things like light but also
things like cutting down bushes.
But gender equality in urban planning is
much more than just safety.
It&#39;s not about individual monsters. It&#39;s
a collective responsibility as well to
make sure that we have a society [music]
where everybody can feel safe.
&gt;&gt; We are Lutan Lousern doesn&#39;t look away.
Lousern citizens standing up for what&#39;s
right. Our online reporting tool lets
people report sexist and queer hostile
harassment and assault in public spaces.
Our goal to help people feel stronger
when they step in. We don&#39;t look away.
Before anyone hits me, please clap.
That&#39;s the signal for a timeout. As long
as that doesn&#39;t happen, we can keep role
playing. You, the ones who could
possibly intervene, can do whatever
feels spontaneously right to you. Often
people come to our courses saying, &quot;I
witnessed something that upset me, but I
didn&#39;t know what to do. I didn&#39;t dare to
intervene or thought I might have made
it worse.&quot;
&gt;&gt; Is this seat taken?
&gt;&gt; Ciao.
[clears throat]
Hello.
&gt;&gt; Hello.
&gt;&gt; I&#39;m David.
&gt;&gt; You? Are you going to Zurich? What&#39;s
your name?
&gt;&gt; I&#39;m not interested in knowing your name.
&gt;&gt; But we&#39;ve seen each other somewhere
before. I think we went to school
together. I have the feeling we know
each other from somewhere.
&gt;&gt; Do you want to have a coffee together?
&gt;&gt; I know a lot of places in Zurich.
Wow. Wow. Wow. What? You&#39;re touching me?
Screw you.
&gt;&gt; She said she&#39;s not interested.
&gt;&gt; Do you know this jerk? Idiot.
&gt;&gt; We&#39;ve often seen in the reporting tool,
I was harassed on the bus. The bus was
full, but no one said anything. No one
helped. That&#39;s where we want to empower
people to step in and say something to
break their silence.
&gt;&gt; Look at me, not your phone. Is this seat
still free?
&gt;&gt; Hello. I&#39;m talking to you.
&gt;&gt; Yes, it&#39;s still free.
&gt;&gt; Thank you.
&gt;&gt; We&#39;re having an argument right now.
Things aren&#39;t so rosy for us.
&gt;&gt; I don&#39;t think you two know each other,
do you? No.
&gt;&gt; Could you sit somewhere else?
&gt;&gt; I think you should move.
&gt;&gt; Are you mother? She can decide for
herself.
&gt;&gt; I think it&#39;s really better if you leave.
Who are you? The police or what?
When no one helps, no one steps in, it&#39;s
extremely distressing. You have the
harassment itself and the lack of
societal support. You start wondering,
was that even harassment? Why didn&#39;t
anyone intervene?
It makes you doubt the situation a
little.
It&#39;s also sending a signal to the
perpetrator. What I&#39;m doing is okay. No
one thought it was worth stepping in at
that moment. But we need to show courage
and step up for people.
You came over pretty quickly. Did you
have an impulse or how did you decide
when to come over?
&gt;&gt; I had the impression that you weren&#39;t
responding to her defensive signals.
&gt;&gt; That&#39;s why I sat next to her before
things escalated any further. Mhm.
Often it can make sense to address the
affected person like would you like to
come with me? If you focus on the
aggressor,
things can escalate.
In Lousern, we receive around five
reports per week proportional to their
larger sizes. Zurich and Burn receive
more in a week. They come in practically
every day. And it&#39;s usually reports from
women experiencing harassment in public
spaces.
&gt;&gt; No.
&gt;&gt; Why not?
&gt;&gt; Can you imagine how much courage it
takes to stand here and confront a man
who could physically outmatch me?
&gt;&gt; I didn&#39;t do anything to you.
&gt;&gt; Yes, you did. You filmed me while I was
running. Probably my butt. Why?
The fear that harassment could lead to a
physical sexualized assault is always
there. [music]
You never know what the other person is
capable of.
&gt;&gt; And in this case, of course, it&#39;s a man
you&#39;re up against. When you display
yourself like that,
&gt;&gt; I only saw you from behind.
&gt;&gt; My clothes aren&#39;t an invitation.
&gt;&gt; I&#39;m not even into butts.
&gt;&gt; I don&#39;t give a
press charges against the man for three
reasons. Number one, he didn&#39;t post the
video publicly. He didn&#39;t forward the
video on to anyone in any way.
And three, I was clothed.
&gt;&gt; Why does it have to involve bare skin to
count as sexual assault? That can&#39;t be
right.
I should be able to run around naked or
dressed in a sack. It shouldn&#39;t matter
if someone films me with sexual intent
and even admits to it on video and
audio. I should be able to go to the
police and they should say, &quot;Very good
that you came. We&#39;ll file a report right
away.&quot;
&gt;&gt; You&#39;re off then?
&gt;&gt; Yes, I&#39;m going.
&gt;&gt; Good. 3 2 Hurry up now.
[music]
&gt;&gt; Why are you so aggressive? I didn&#39;t do
anything to you.
&gt;&gt; Because that wasn&#39;t a pleasant
experience. It&#39;ll stay with me all day
and tomorrow and the day after.
&gt;&gt; Then why do you wear pants like that?
&gt;&gt; Because I&#39;m jogging.
&gt;&gt; So those are normal pants. Do we really
want to discuss this?
&gt;&gt; I&#39;m sorry. I&#39;m sorry.
&gt;&gt; Ready,
&gt;&gt; set, go.
[music]
&gt;&gt; Ultimately, the question is not if a
woman will experience sexualized
violence,
but when.
For decades, it was the case that
prevention efforts focused almost
exclusively on victims or potential
victims. We looked at women&#39;s behaviors
and what they could do differently.
More than once on my way home, I&#39;ve
pretended to be on the phone or actually
called someone. It&#39;s one of the classic
things you&#39;re taught to do as a girl.
Always keep an eye on your drink when
you&#39;re out. Make sure you don&#39;t drink
too much.
There&#39;s advice to follow about clothing,
about behavior, especially behavior
toward men.
You can make a whole list. Carry your
key in your hand so you can use it as a
weapon
or tell someone when you&#39;re leaving,
send me your location, all those things.
The big problem with that kind of advice
is [clears throat] that it always
includes a form of victim blaming.
If I grow up believing I have to follow
certain clothing rules to not be
sexually harassed and then I don&#39;t
follow them, dress provocatively and end
up being harassed.
Of course, I&#39;d feel like it was my own
fault.
[music]
Was that really sexual harassment or am
I just being too sensitive?
In that sense, men were relieved of
their responsibility. People said,
&quot;Okay, now we&#39;ll focus on women. Give
them advice so that they hopefully don&#39;t
experience sexual violence.&quot; But
sexualized violence can only be
prevented by those who commit it, not by
those who experience it.
So far, I&#39;ve only spoken about the
people who are affected. It&#39;s safe to
assume that the vast majority of
perpetrators are men. Regardless of
who&#39;s affected, even men who experience
violence usually experience it at the
hands of other men.
&gt;&gt; There&#39;s enormous potential in working
with boys. There are so many boys who
have questions and are looking for
answers.
daycare centers, schools. There are lots
of women there. Boys mostly grow up with
female role models. Then at some point
they realize these are women, but I&#39;m
different.
&gt;&gt; Soccer players are a big thing depending
on where we are. Politicians at the
moment too. Donald Trump comes up
frequently with some boys.
[music] Those
are the kinds of male role models I
often encounter, the ones that take up a
lot of space in our society. That&#39;s why
it&#39;s all the more important for fathers
to serve as positive role models.
Ask fathers, what kind of masculinity do
you present? What kind do you want to
pass on to your children? What kind of
role model do you want to be?
&gt;&gt; [music]
[snorts]
&gt;&gt; There are factors that boys lose during
their socialization.
[music]
What emotion am I perceiving? They can
still name that well up to fourth grade.
But if we look six or seven years later,
unfortunately many have already lost
that. It&#39;s been overridden by societal
expectations of masculinity. They lose
that connection. I believe that&#39;s where
self assertion courses can help.
It&#39;s really important that you listen to
your feelings. Don&#39;t just think, I&#39;m not
going to listen to that.
A self assertion course shouldn&#39;t be
confused with a self-defense course.
Self assertion means sensing your
boundaries, recognizing them, and
communicating them. It also means
accepting help or offering help. Boys
are often good at giving help. That&#39;s
seen as a masculine trait. But what
starts to get harder, even in fourth
grade, is accepting help.
I think we can really learn something
from these fourth grade boys. Their
wholeheartedness, their carefree
natures, they have a lot of energy.
They come in and take up space very
naturally. That&#39;s nice because they
invest that energy into play.
&gt;&gt; [music]
&gt;&gt; The downside is that they take up space
and forget that others have less because
of it.
Some of them struggle to take
responsibility for their actions.
Meanwhile, girls often take on a lot of
responsibility for the atmosphere in
class. For instance,
and Dennis called
Zanti, come to me. You communicated. You
did it. You stood up for another as a
class, as a team. You looked for
solutions and you succeeded.
Today at noon, he was arrested on
suspicion of attempted murder. He&#39;s a
Swedish citizen, 33 years old, residing
in the municipality of Umea.
&gt;&gt; The police got a tip that they should
try his DNA.
and he was probably the first one to say
no thanks to to a DNA swab. Uh which
made the police curious.
This is a paper from when he was caught
the day after. It says, &quot;How&#39;s it?&quot; Here
is it. The court ruled him to be in
prison for 14 years. So he was released
after 10 years.
I think that the Hogaman and case really
influenced men and men&#39;s behavior
towards women.
It helped to raise awareness of the
perception of how a lot of women feel in
public space and and [music] kind of to
create a sense of empathy.
&gt;&gt; Boys aren&#39;t violent by nature. Our
social structure puts boys in a role
where they come to recognize violence as
a legitimate way to enforce their will.
[music]
So many feelings are coming up now.
They come up when I watch the video and
talk about it.
I&#39;ve come out of the situation a lot
stronger, though.
&gt;&gt; [music]
&gt;&gt; The response has been so supportive and
there&#39;s been so much encouragement.
[music]
To any parents who are worried about
their daughter&#39;s safety, I&#39;d say talk to
your son about it.
[music]